High noon in old Cheyenne, I'd like to
call the meeting of the Finance
Committee to order for the August 18th.
Um if you're in the room, please turn
off your cell phones or vibrator.
Making public comment, clearly identify
yourself. In making public comment
online, use the raised hand function.
You're here in person, approach the
podium, turn on the microphone. And at
the completion of this agenda, no
additional business will be discussed.
And most importantly,
all communication goes through the
chair. With that, Chair Clerk, first
item.
>> Number 8C, memorandum of understanding
between the City of Cheyenne and
Cheyenne Police Department and Laramie
County School District number one for
the School Resource Officers Program.
>> Staff report.
Welcome, Officer.
>> Thank you.
Uh Mr. Chair, through you to the
committee. You have before you a um
contract between the Cheyenne Police
Department and Laramie County School
District number one to provide seven
school resource officers and one school
resource officer sergeant for our local
Cheyenne schools.
Uh they will compensate 75% of the
officers' salaries, um and that amount
comes to $765,615.09.
Oh, sorry.
I am Lieutenant Kevin Malatesta with the
Cheyenne Police Department.
>> Thank you. Uh questions from the
committee for our um
lieutenant Is it you
>> Malatesta.
>> Malatesta. Did you say lieutenant?
>> Yes.
>> Oh.
You got a promotion from the last time I
saw you.
>> Yep.
>> Congratulations.
>> Thank you.
>> So, any uh
comments from or questions from the
committee for Officer Malatesta?
>> Um Mr. Chair, just
for the record, this is a continuation
of this annual agreement that we've had
with the Cheyenne Police Department and
School District for
as long as I've been on council and
probably far beyond that. So,
>> Uh okay.
We'll go to public comment in the room.
Any public comment in the room on this
item?
Any public comment online?
Public comment online.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, members of the Finance
Committee, Charles Miller for the
record. We are sitting here today on the
precipice of another
multi-hundred-thousand-dollar
rubber stamp session, and the paperwork
on item 8C proves that this
administration's math simply does not
compute. Turn to page one of the
attachment A, item 1A of this school
resource officer agreement. It states in
black and white the district is
responsible for paying 70%
was 75% then written in of the combined
estimated annual salary and benefits.
Let that sink in. 70%, 75%. If your
legal team in the police department
cannot proofread a basic 5% math
contradiction representing a $38,000
billing gap on a $765,615
and 9 cent contract, how can we trust
you to manage the millions of dollars
flowing through for accounts? But,
this is not a new issue. It is a
historical rerun of last year's SRO
contract debacle, where you rushed to
committee with a contract stating the
district would pay 75% for a total of
$650,000,
but printed the numerical dollar value
as 555 plus overtime, forcing a
last-minute scramble to clean up your
paperwork. This administration has
repeatedly proven itself incapable of
running a basic spell check before
demanding our signatures. Beyond the
clerical incompetent look at the
structural surrender of public funds
built into this deal. The public
emergency subsidy section 5Q, this
agreement dictates that SROs can be
immediately recalled for public
emergencies at any time with absolutely
no penalty to the city. Yet, the school
district is billed for full-time
academic coverage. Laramie County School
District number one taxpayers are
actively subsidizing standard municipal
police patrols, while their schools are
left unstaffed during a recall.
The MOU explicitly seals all SRO audio
and video recordings as peace officer
recordings under
Wyoming statute 16-4-201
AXI,
declaring them the sole property of the
city that cannot be released
public. You're actively using public
school funds to run cameras on children,
while preemptively hiding the footage
from open records transparency. Mr.
Chairman, this contract is slipshod,
mathematically compromised liability
trap. Do not approve this item today.
Stop the clock. Send it back to the city
attorney's desk and demand a contract
that respects both basic arithmetic and
the taxpayers of Laramie County. Thank
you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment
online?
Okay, seeing none, we'll come back to
the committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
seconded by Councilman White. Any other
discussion? Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you,
just clarification for the public.
Again, this is uh
standard agreement there.
Cameras in the schools are not the Flock
cameras. They've been there like 20
years and they're closed circuit, not
the same. Thank you.
>> Okay, all those in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And seeing that there's no
opposed, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee at the next meeting of
the governing body will be to approve.
Next item.
>> Number 8D, professional service
agreement between the city of Cheyenne
and Adurra Group Incorporated for
operational modification at the Pershing
Converse, Pershing Converse and 19th
Street roundabout.
>> Staff report.
>> Uh Mr. Chair, through you, Aaron Gates,
city staff engineer. But this item is a
professional services agreement with
Adurra Group to look at the roundabout
at the intersection of Pershing Converse
and 19th to make some operational
modifications so that it functions
better.
It will include a review of an analysis
that was completed in 2019
uh as well as prepare a recommendation
of findings and then prepare design
plans so that this can be implemented
hopefully next summer.
I stand for any questions.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Chair, through you.
Thank you, ma'am. I appreciate that. Um
I'm looking at here and for the public
to know it's the Adurra here on page
one.
Um I saw that the uh
in 2006 and that five-year period there
were 125 collisions. How many collisions
have there been uh recently? I'd say
going from 2020 to 2026.
>> Mr. Chairman, through you. Uh sir, I do
not know what the number of collisions
are, but that data can be provided
through WYDOT to this consultant as part
of this analysis and review.
>> Follow.
Go ahead.
>> Uh thank you to you. Thank you, ma'am. I
guess what the my big question is what's
the ultimate goal with this? Like, is it
to reduce lanes, expand it, better have
better signage? What's the ultimate goal
with this uh study?
>> Mr. Chair, through you, the ultimate
goal is to look at what was recommended
back in 2019, see if those
recommendations are still valid, or if
any other recommendations due to
uh
changes to practices, and looking how
modern roundabouts function, if then
anything like that comes out to
implement in this roundabout.
>> Good.
Oh, thank thank you for that. Um I guess
my uh question is, what are some of the
recommendations in 2019? Were any of
them implemented?
>> Uh Mr. Chair, through you, some of the
recommendations have been implemented,
such as
uh updating the signage and striping of
the roundabout. I I believe they got rid
of the fishhook um
diagram that was on some of the signs
that was confusing, so it's more of the
straight arrow to indicate lanage of the
signs,
um
and then some payment markings
uh I believe were done last year uh with
our thermoplastic project.
>> All right, thank you.
>> Any questions from Councilman White?
>> No, sir.
>> Okay, we'll close that part and move on
to public comment in the room on this
item.
Any public comment in the room?
Any public comment online?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Mr. Chairman, members of the Finance
Committee, Charles Miller for the
record.
Um uh before you today
to demand that you immediately pull item
8D from the uh
consent agenda. Oh, it's not on the
consent agenda, is it? Um
>> No.
>> Uh
so uh this is for $186,500.
Is that correct?
>> Correct.
>> Um, and it's an outsourced engineering
contract.
Um,
it it's a
This is one of the most embarrassing
infrastructure boondoggles in the modern
history of the city of Cheyenne. Under
this agreement, you were preparing to
hand a Dura Group $186,500
of optional 1% sales tax funds to
develop bid-ready drawings to modify the
Pershing Converse and 19th Street
roundabout. But, when we audit the scope
of work and the history of this
intersection, we find an administrative
loop of circular planning and structural
failure.
This roundabout was completed in
December 2013 to replace an intersection
that had 125 collisions.
It failed almost immediately. By 2017,
the metro metropolitan planning
organization had to launch an expensive
public safety campaign just to teach
local citizens how to drive through it.
When that failed, the city spent
uh, more public funds in 2019 to hire
MTJ Engineering to write a comprehensive
report detailing how to fix driver
confusion and reduce the ongoing
collision rate. Now, in 2026, Adura's
exhibit A reveals that you are paying
them, again, $186,500
to develop an independent review of
current roundabout operations and
compare findings with the 2019 MTJ
report. You are quite literally paying a
premium consultant to study a study of
your own failed design. Look at the
actual physical changes Adura is tasked
to design. After spending millions of
dollars to build a dual-lane modern
roundabout gateway, your engineering
department is now preparing to spend
another $186,500
to paint over the pavement, restrict
lanes, and choke it down to a single
lane
because your engineering
original engineering design was so poor
that drivers coming down the hill can
see the entire intersection, prompting
them to race in to beat their neighbors.
To fix your own visibility engineering
failure, you are now designing
southbound screening, which is a polite
way of saying you're going to erect a
giant wall to block drivers vision so
they are forced to slow down. You're
spending close to $200,000
to castrate your own roundabout and
build a blind spot wall. This is the
exact same roundabout project that
dragged the city through five years of
toxic expensive litigation with Mary
Rose Ramirez at 2247 East 19th Street.
Previous engineering department was
directed to minimize right of way
acquisition. In doing so, they purchased
two houses on the northwest corner that
they did not even need, while completely
ignoring Ms. Ramirez's property on the
northeast corner. You literally designed
her home into a physical box with zero
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Your time is up.
Any other public comment online?
No other public comment online?
Come back to the committee. Any comments
or questions?
Seeing none, ready to vote. All in
favor, signify with
I'll make a motion.
I'll motion for discussion.
I'll I'll
Comments or questions from the
committee?
>> I have some.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you,
I thank everybody for the comments. One
thing about roundabouts, they actually
do reduce severe collisions. I've
actually looked at um
all videos and studies. One was done in
a suburb of
Indianapolis. I mean, they have a lot. I
know we're not going to go to that far,
but they actually have reduced a lot of
severe collisions.
We did hear there was a study done about
signage. And actually, I have talked
with constituents. They said improve the
signage. Improve the signage. They don't
want reduced to one lane. I've even
talked to people who are in the trucking
industry. They said that'd would a
nightmare if it was reduced to one lane.
So,
we already know we need to do with the
signage aspect. I think that's a fairly
easy fix that probably would cost about
as much as a study.
So, that's why I'm going to vote no on
this because again, we People I'm saying
prove the signage.
I think we can prove the signage
signage.
That probably be the easiest fix right
there.
And educate the public on how to use our
roundabouts, which they do in that one
town there or the suburb Indianapolis.
So, again, they go to the extreme of
having over 100. No, we're not going to
go that way.
But,
just food for thought. Thank you.
>> Any comments or questions from
Councilman White?
>> Uh yes, Mr. Chairman, through you. I
really appreciate my colleagues
uh from Ward 3's comments regarding
this. Um I was on council when um
the major redesign was done.
Um and while our community already had a
roundabout that's been very uh
successful up at uh Vanda High, um this
one proved much more controversial. This
I think for folks like me who've lived
here a really long time, this particular
intersection has always been
extremely complex.
Um I supported putting in the roundabout
originally. Um I think it has worked. Um
I do agree with Councilman Moody that I
think uh
I think improving the signage is
probably the
um quickest and most efficient way of um
of uh improving it further.
Um
But, uh one thing I I do want to say is
uh the the person who complained about
the expensive public education campaign
when this uh a roundabout first went
into place, I I have to push back on
that. That was something that uh the
community wanted. I know uh police,
safety folks, the council at the time
all wanted an extensive public education
campaign put out for for this particular
roundabout. And so that was done
by request from virtually everyone at
the time. So
that said, I I will be supporting this
item today. I I do want to uh
receive updates from the engineer's
office on this before major construction
um
goes forward because I I
I would oppose reducing
number of lanes as well.
>> Hey, all those in favor to accept the
bid, signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those no.
The chair will not vote on this one. I
think it's best that we take this to the
full committee next Monday to discuss
it.
So the recommendation there will be no
recommendation from the committee at the
next meeting of the governing body on
this item.
Next item, please.
>> Number 9A contract modification number
one to contract number 8324 between the
city of Cheyenne and the Cheyenne
Downtown Development Authority for the
fiscal year beginning July 1st, 2026 and
ending June 30th, 2027.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon, chair and members of the
committee. My name is Sophia Maze. I'm
the Downtown Development Authority
Executive Director.
Before you today is a proposed amendment
to the fiscal year 2027 memorandum of
understanding between the city and the
Cheyenne Downtown Development Authority.
Under the current agreement, the city of
Cheyenne supports the DDA by providing
personnel assistance through the
planning and development department.
Following a recommendation from the DDA
cost-benefit task force, the DDA Board
of Directors voted to transfer the DDA
staff to the Community Recreation and
Events Department at its special meeting
on August 7th, 2026.
Board also approved the amended MOU
before you today.
This transfer is supported by the nature
of the DDA's work. The DDA administrates
Excuse me, administers several
established programs including the
downtown planter program, the downtown
banner program, and multiple property
improvement grants. It assists the city
in downtown capital projects through
communication support and building its
capacity to manage, and it is currently
building its capacity to manage smaller
initiatives in including lighting,
wayfinding, and gateway enhancements.
The Community Recreation and Events
Department already performs comparable
work on a considerable scale, overseeing
12 divisions focused on parks,
beautification, and public facilities.
The department currently manages and
maintains several downtown assets
including the Depot, the Plaza, the
Spiker Garage, and currently
redeveloping the pump house for its
downtown dedicated clean and safe
division.
CRE provides downtown street tree
watering
through urban forestry, and has
established downtown events such as
Fridays on the Plaza, and partners on
facilitation of Cheyenne Frontier Days
events such as Cheyenne Day, the grand
parades, and pancake breakfasts.
This proposal positions the DDA to
collaborate with CRE who has
demonstrated execution capability.
And as the DDA continues to develop into
a stable and capable city board.
It should be noted that under the
amendments, the DDA board will still
have authority over the DDA mill levy,
budget, and strategic direction, and
funds will remain separate from the
larger department unless an expense is
approved by the board.
DDA staff would continue to be city
employees and retain their existing city
benefits, and going forward, DDA staff
would be hired and directed jointly by
the DDA Board of Directors and the
Director of the Community Recreation and
Events Department.
Staff respectfully recommends the
committee approve the amended fiscal
year 2027 MOU consistent with the DDA
board's actions on August 7th. Thank you
and I stand for questions.
>> Any comments or questions for the
director from the committee?
>> Uh Mr. Chair, uh
Councilman White here. I would just like
to make a quick comment. Um
as Sophia noted, this uh
change in MOU is was uh unanimously
redacted read uh recommended uh by a
task force within uh the DDA board. It
was also voted on
uh by the entire DDA board at their last
meeting. And uh during that meeting,
this uh change in MOU was unanimously
supported by folks who had given public
comment at that meeting.
Um
so um
if you read through it, it's just
basically uh some grammatical changes
and then noting the change from uh
planning placement of DDA in the
planning office to uh community
recreation and events.
>> Thank you, Councilman White. Uh any
further comments or questions from the
committee?
Seeing none, we'll go to public comment
in the room.
Any public comment in the room?
Seeing none, go to public comment
online.
>> Ms. Volk, you can go ahead.
>> Thank you. This is Wendy Volk. I'm the
vice chair of the Downtown Development
Authority.
Um we are excited and delighted about
this opportunity to align uh the
Downtown Development Authority mission.
We appreciate all the hard work that
Sophia and our team have placed on this
potential alignment with the community
recreation and events and we would
appreciate your support. We'd be happy
to answer any questions.
>> Thank you, Ms. Volk.
Uh there any other further comments
online?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Mr. Chairman, members of the Finance
Committee, Charles Miller for the
record. Um I'm before you to demand the
immediate rejection of the Downtown
Development Authority's
uh fiscal year '27 work program MOU.
Under this amended agreement, you are
proposing a structural shift that
borders
um on the farcical. Uh
So, let me ask you this. You're
transferring the DDA's professional
economic development and blight
remediation staff out of the Planning
and Development Department and housing
them under the Community Recreation and
Events Department. Is that true?
Is that Is that correct?
>> We're getting you an answer.
>> Mr. Chair, through you, yes, that is
correct.
>> Oh, okay. Um well, let's look at the
absolute absurdity, the historical
failures, and the fiduciary black hole
that this MOU represents.
Um the Downtown Development Authority is
a statutory body corporate designed to
combat urban blight, coordinate
high-level commercial property
development, and and drive capital
investment. Yet, today, you're placing
this critical economic agency in the
exact same municipal department that
manages beer fests, youth soccer, park
lawn mowers, and employee picnics. This
is the ultimate structural white flag, a
complete admission that you do not know
how to run a cohesive urban planning
strategy.
This transfer is a direct result of the
DDA's chronic decades-long
administrative chaos. The city's
archives show that the DDA has operated
under a revolving door of board members
and executive directors, spinning
through Amy Surdam, Amber Ash, Dominic
Bravo, and a host of others in rapid
succession. This volatility is so severe
that local downtown business and
property owners have actively bypassed
the DDA entirely and organizing their
own independent private promotional
groups because they are tired of waiting
for the DDA to execute the basics. This
committee is preparing to authorize
hundreds of thousands of dollars of
taxpayer money from our highly strained
general fund to pay 100% of DDA staff
salaries and benefits. Yet, section 4.4A
of this MOU explicitly states DDA staff
shall act under the authority of the DDA
board and not under the direction of the
city or any of its departments. This is
surrender of municipal oversight. You're
asking Cheyenne taxpayers to write a
blank check for salaries while legally
stripping city management of any lawful
supervisory or disciplinary control over
those same employees. That is not
economic development. That is taxpayer
funded payroll subsidy with zero
accountability. If you want to know how
the DDA exercises its independent
discretion, we only have to look at
their recorded history.
DDA leadership literally confessed on
the record that they don't want to fix
sidewalks proactively. Instead, they
wait for code enforcement to threaten
business owners so they can swoop in
with public money and look like the
savior.
The DDA spent thousands on a parking
striping pilot project and when the
paint began to wash away almost
immediately, they admitted on the record
that they deliberately bought the
cheapest paint possible that would only
last 2 years just to see if the pilot
worked.
Just recently this
>> Mr. Miller, your time is up. Any further
public comment online?
Further comment
online.
Okay, we'll come back to the committee.
What's your pleasure?
Uh Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved and seconded.
Uh any further comments from the
committee? Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you. Uh
just for the public to know, it's really
just changing the agreement. I
originally was opposed, but after doing
research, it makes sense it's in
community recreation cuz again of what
they do and also too in terms of the
improving the downtown that fits more
with it because Muni Recta has a safe
and clean program. So, make more sense
there is they can coordinate better. So,
it's actually, you know, reducing waste
and actually helping make it more
efficient. So, that's why I'll be in
support of this. Thank you.
>> Any further public Any further comments
from the committee?
>> Yes, Mr. Chair. Mr. Councilman Moody
absolutely nailed it.
Um you know, I was initially reluctant
when I this move was suggested, but to
what he said, I did some research. It's
actually quite common for other DDAs to
be to work in collaboration with other
uh
communities' clean and safe departments.
It just so happens that our clean and
safe department falls under community
recreation and events. So, it is
actually
uh not out of the norm whatsoever.
>> Thank you. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Okay, seeing that that vote is
unanimous, the recommendation at the
next meeting of the governing body will
be to adopt. Next item, please.
>> Number 10A, consideration of bid number
S-22-26
for a contract between the City of
Cheyenne and Legacy Construction Group
for the Christensen Road Detention
Erosion Mitigation Project.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon, Chairman Escobedo, and
members of the Finance Committee. Tom
Copsey, the engineer.
Um before you and your for your
consideration, obviously, is the bid
between uh City of Cheyenne and Legacy
Construction for the um Christensen Road
Detention Erosion Mitigation Project. Um
I've been reporting on this for several
weeks. Um I am now telling you right now
that I my recommendation to you is,
regardless of what direction we go, we
have semi some concepts approved by the
UP, but it's going to be a significant
enough change that I'm asking that I
recommend to actually cancel the award
and do not award this contract. At this
time, um, it's going to be materially
too much difference, so we'll rebid it
um at a later date.
If you If with that I'll have any
questions that you might have for me.
>> Okay. Councilman Moody again. Thank you,
Mr. Chairman, through uh Thank you, Mr.
Cobb. I know it's been a lot of work
with this. Um
with the railroad they You said they
want steel. I mean
obviously this is public infrastructure
in the public and is vital for our
community.
What What cost do you see uh What What
are potential costs? A million dollars?
1.2?
>> Chairman Eskew through you to Councilman
Moody.
>> Uh approximately $280,000
if we have to go steel.
>> Thank Thank you. I have no more
questions.
>> Do you have any questions, Councilman
White?
>> I do not.
>> Okay, with that we'll go to public
comment in the room.
Is there any public comment in the room?
Public comment online?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Mr. Chairman, members of the Finance
Committee, Charles Miller for the
record. I want to formally thank our
city engineer, Tom Cobb, for finally ex-
exercising the basic fiduciary sobriety
that this administration has lacked for
years. His recommendation today to not
uh recommend the award for the Christian
Road contract is a total absolute
vindication of the exact
math and history that was just laid out.
Um Cobb's recommendation is a direct
admission of a simple undeniable
reality. You cannot hand a blank check
of $314,000 of public money to a
contractor while you were locked in an
active easement standoff with the Union
Pacific Railroad. To do so would have
guaranteed a massive taxpayer-funded
change order the second UP demanded
their steel pipe.
But let us not pretend this is an
isolated incident. This is a forced
administrative retreat because poison
paperwork was exposed to the light. And
now that the city engineer has shown
this committee what actual fiduciary
oversight looks like, I expect you to
apply that same exact standard of
sobriety
um to
uh the the rest of uh what you guys are
working on. Um
if
uh
if you have the sense to table
Christensen Road because of incomplete
paperwork
um
I'm sorry.
Uh
I believe that you probably uh you guys
probably are going to
not want me to uh
mention any of the other items that you
guys are working on today. So, I will uh
just stand by saying that
um
that uh you guys are uh protecting the
public purse by stopping a bad deal
before it's signed.
Um
uh
thank you.
>> Thank you. Any further public comment
online?
Seeing none, we'll come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
Can I get a motion?
Seeing that there's no motion, the there
will be no recommendation from the
finance committee. Did you want to make
a comment on that?
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. Through you,
Alfred Parnell, the reason we didn't
make a motion is because it was
requested by the city engineer to cancel
it. So, this will just not be
recommended. So, just for just a
preliminary procedure. Thank you.
>> Correct. And there will be no
recommendation from the finance
committee at the next meeting in the
governing body. Seeing that that's the
end of our agenda, we are adjourned.